A Guide to the Anna Laura Lindsay Papers, 1898-1937
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Anna Laura Lindsay Papers, 1898-1937
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
1959-7
100 pieces
Some personal and business correspondence of the founder of the Department of Music at Virginia State University. There are also a large number of photographs.
Anna Laura Lindsay
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Anna Laura Lindsay was born in Lexington, Kentucky, November 14, 1876. she attended the Chandler Normal A.M.A School in Lexington, Kentucky, and entered Fisk University in 1893 where she completed the Normal School course in 1897 and the music course in 1898.
Miss Lindsay taught at the Knox Institute, another A.M.A school at athens, Georgia, during 1898-9 and left there to begin her work at the Normal and Collegiate Institute of Virginia. Miss Lindsay taught English, Physiology, Arithimitic, Piano and served as director of all music activities in the Virginia Normal and Collegiate Institute from 1899-1902. When the legislature reduced the status of the school to that of a industrial institute, she continued her work in music and when college coures were re-activated in 1922, she became head of the department of music.
In order to continue her own professional growth Miss Lindsay studied at the Virginia State College, the University of Pennsylvania and at Columbia University. She earned the degrees of Bachelor of Science (1927), the Master's of Arts (1928) from Teacher's College of Columbia University, with the special diploma in Music Education.
Miss Lindsay organized men's and women's glee clubs and the choral society at Virginia State. As head of the Department of music she was instrumental in organizing the Virginia State Music Festival patterened at first on that of the Fisk Festival's, which included school and church groups.
Miss Lindsay organized the Fisk Club at Virginia State College in the early 1900's and remained as President for a number of years. Miss Lindsay retired from Virginia State in 1947.
Scope and Content Information
Some personal and business correspondence. There are also a large number of photographs.
Series Description
Series I Correspondence Writings, and information on Virginia State University.
Series II Financial Bills and reciepts
Series III Affiliations Some information about Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority and the National Association of College Women.
Series IV Literary Speeches and Writings Speeches and writings pertaining to the teaching and studying of music.
Series V Printed Broad sides and programs
Series VI Photographs A photograph album and a number of photographs many unidentified.
Series VII Printed News clippings collected center mainly on topics relative to the civil rights struglgle and the emergence of African independence.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence 1898,1958,n.d. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Financial
  - Bills and Reciepts 1904 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Affiliations
  - Alpha Kappa Alpha, and the National Association of College Women 144, 1942 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Literary Speeches and Writings
  - Speech-the 3 "P's" of Musicians (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Writings "Music for the matoaca Training School (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Writings-untitled (Box-folder 1:6)
- Printed
  - Program-Cleota Collins 1927,1935,1937 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Programs-Cleota Collins 1954 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Brochure-E.Azaleca Hackley n.d. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Song-Gordon B. Hancock 1965 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Programs-Programs at Virginia State (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Programs and Announcements-Va. State Catalogue-the florida Baptist Academy 1913-1914 (Box-folder 1:12)
    Bulletin-State Courses of Study High School of Virginia Music 1932, Bulletin-Study Course for Virginia State Curriculum Program.. 1932, Report-The National Council of the YMCA 1938, Bulletin-Tenative courses of study in Music Elementary and High School 1938, Bulletin-list of Films, Slides, and recordings for Virginia public Schools 1940, Bulletin-Tenative courses ofstudy in music for high Schools 1943, Book-Music, Education, Curriculum, Committee Reports 1945.
- Photos
  - Family and Friends
    - Family Photo Album
    - The Lindsay Family (Box-folder 2:1)
    - The Lindsay Family (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Lindsay Family 1885 (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Lindsay Family 1885 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Mrs.Lindsay (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Mrs. Lindsay (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Anna Laura Lindsay (Neg.) (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Anna Laura Lindsay and mother (Box-folder 2:8)
    - Lindsay papers and Charles Lindsay (Box-folder 2:9)
    - Anna Laura Lindsay (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Anna Laura Lindsay (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Anna and Charles (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Charles Lindsay (Box-folder 2:13)
    - Charles Lindsay (Box-folder 2:14)
    - Charles Lindsay (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Friends
    - Addie (Box-folder 3:1)
    - Baily, C. (Box-folder 3:2)
    - The "Bell" Sisters (Box-folder 3:3)
    - Branson, Herman (Box-folder 3:4)
    - Brown,Samuel (Box-folder 3:5)
    - Carroal,Charles (Box-folder 3:6)
    - Carter,Patterson (Box-folder 3:7)
    - Chatfield, Grace (Box-folder 3:8)
    - Chew, Marguerite (Box-folder 3:9)
    - John Chilos (Box-folder 3:10)
    - Clarke,Elise (Box-folder 3:11)
    - Cora and Maggie (Box-folder 3:12)
    - The Dabney's (Box-folder 3:13)
    - Davison,Minnie (Box-folder 3:14)
    - Edna Colson (Box-folder 3:15)
    - Female-n.d. (Box-folder 3:16)
    - Gandy, Theodore (Box-folder 3:17)
    - Grace (Box-folder 3:18)
    - Groups (Box-folder 3:19)
    - Harris (Box-folder 3:20)
    - Harrison, Gladys (Box-folder 3:21)
    - Howard,Otelia Shields (Box-folder 3:22)
    - Jimmie (Box-folder 3:23)
    - Johnson (Box-folder 3:24)
    - The Jones (Box-folder 3:25)
    - Lauvena (Folder 3:26)
    - Lindsay (Box-folder 3:27)
    - Male-n.d. (Box-folder 3:28)
    - Male-n.d. (Box-folder 3:29)
    - Male-n.d. (Box-folder 3:30)
    - Mason,Ella-1896 (Box-folder 3:31)
    - Mittie (Box-folder 3:32)
    - Molsey,Marguerite (Box-folder 3:33)
    - Olcott, Chauncey (Box-folder 3:34)
    - Samuels,Alice (Box-folder 3:35)
    - Simms (Box-folder 3:36)
    - Starks,Nellie (Box-folder 3:37)
    - Talifero (Box-folder 3:38)
    - The Thompsons (Box-folder 3:39)
    - Troy,Fannie (Box-folder 3:40)
    - U.S.O-n.d. (Box-folder 3:41)
    - Wright (Box-folder 3:42)
    - unidentified Female (Box-folder 3:43-48)
    - Unidentified Male (Box-folder 3:49-51)
    - Micellaneous-Floral Scene (Box-folder 3:52)
    - Micellaneous-Group (Box-folder 3:53)
    - Micellaneous-shopping scene-n.d. (Box-folder 3:54)